So,
welcome back.
We will now deal here
today with properties of Petri nets.
I had already announced this at
the end of the last lecture.
As
a reminder:
We had last dealt with
reachability graphs, respectively with their construction.
That was the example
from the last lecture.
There was this Petri net, and I
had set up the reachability graph for it.
And based on that, I
had already intuitively discussed some properties.
For example, the fact that
there is a dead end here.
That you can get into a situation
where the Petri net can't fire anymore.
But I had also
discussed other properties here.
These are, of course, properties
of the Petri net, actually.
But we can recognize them
in part better or at all
by setting up and
analyzing the reachability graph.
It will be the same for
the properties we are looking at today.
They will be properties
of Petri nets, but
they will be discussed or
defined on the reachability graph.
And we will start
first with terms related
to liveness or
even non-liveness, deadlock.
Later, other properties
will be added.
But the first
small family of properties
will be about
aliveness and its opposite.
There are several terms there, and the
first one is not just called "aliveness",
but
"strong aliveness".
Here is
the definition first.
So a Petri net is called "strong liveness"
if .... and then there is a definition here.
So it must hold that for every
single transition t (the Petri net can have
several transitions, after all) and for every marking
reachable from m0 (we remember, m0 was the
starting marking), let's call that
m, there is a marking m',
which in turn is reachable from
m, and for which t is activated.
This is
a multi-level definition:
For every t and
every marking m reachable
from m0, let there
be another marking m', etc.
What does
this mean intuitively?
Basically,
it means:
Let the Petri net
run arbitrarily from the initial
marking without thinking of
any special transition t.
So you let
it run first.
At some point one says
"Stop" and has a marking m.
Now it must be possible to continue
working from there (wherever you are) in such
a way that at some point you
still have the opportunity to fire t.
It must not be possible that
on the way from m0 to
m one has somehow maneuvered
oneself into a corner of the
reachability graph, from where one never
again gets the opportunity to fire t.
Then the Petri net is strongly alive
if that holds for every transition t.
This means, of course, that then t can
be fired arbitrarily many times, infinitely many times.
But this is not
all that the property says.
Strong liveness is indeed
a very strong notion.
One can read off the
property from the reachability graph.
One can also transfer what is written
here in the definition to the reachability graph.
Then it
is ultimately said:
From each node of the graph a transition
must be reachable which is labeled with t.
From "every node of the graph", that
is just all markings reachable from m0.
So if we say, "for
every marking m reachable from m0",
that is equivalent to saying,
"from every node of the reachability
graph" (there are only
reachable markings in there).
So from there, you have to be able
to get somewhere where t is activated again.
That is, from each
node of the reachability
graph, another node must be
reachable, or perhaps the same node,
from which a transition
can be made with t.
This corresponds to the
fact that t is activated.
For example, is this true for
our example Petri net from last week?
For this
Petri net?
Does this have the property that
if one makes any transitions (any
number, any length) starting
from this starting marking m0,
it is guaranteed that in
whatever marking m one is
then, a marking m' is reachable from
there, where t1 is fireable, for example?
Or conversely, we first
fix on t1 and ask:
Is it the case that for every
reachable marking m it is then still possible
to reach an m'
from which t1 is fireable?
And for t1 the answer must be
"yes", for t2 the answer must be "yes",
for t3 the
answer must be "yes".
If for all three the answer is "Yes" in
each case, then this Petri net would be strongly alive.
You can then
think about this here:
What happens if
I fire here?
What
could happen?
Can I guarantee that I
can always fire t3, for example?
We can answer that
on the reachability graph.
Is it true here that
from any node it is possible
to reach a node
where t1 is fireable?
No, it is certainly not true
because there is the dead end.
So we take
as t our t1.
Then it is indeed the case that there
is a marking m reachable from m0, and
starting from it there is no
m' in which t1 is fireable.
So starting from this node
there is no reachable node
from which t1 or even
t2 or t3 can be fired.
In that case, it would not even
matter whether one focuses on t1, t2, t3.
Because it is the case for
all three that there is at least
one node, this one, from which you can
never fire t1 or t2 or t3 again.
And it's not the
only dead end either.
For every dead end
in this reachability graph, we
would have this phenomenon that, of
course, transitions are never executable again.
Otherwise, it wouldn't
be a dead end.
That is, related
to this Petri net:
You can have
"deadlocking" sequences here.
That will be somehow, if here for
example t2 and t3 are not fired sensibly,
alternately; but after firing t1, then
there would be here below two tokens,
for example these both with t3
moved up and thereby prevented that
ever t1 is fireable again; and then
of course also no other transition more.
So here the answer would actually be
that this Petri net that we have
seen is not strongly
alive in that sense.
That would
be "strong liveness."
If there
is "strong aliveness",
then surely there is also
a notion of "weak aliveness".
And perhaps our Petri
net at least fulfills this.
So what does
"weak aliveness" mean?
A Petri net is weakly lively
if for each transition t there
is a marking m reachable from
m0 for which t is activated.
With the strong liveness it was said
that for each transition t and each
marking m attainable from m0 it is
so that one can fire t sometime still.
While here it
is only said:
For every transition t there must
be a marking m reachable from m0
for which
t is activated.
And
not:
For every marking m reachable
from m0 it must be possible
to reach m' for
which t is activated.
So this is a weaker requirement, because here
you can make a convenient choice, so to speak
So as the person who wants to
try to prove that a Petri net is
weakly lively, here one can sort of
choose a favorable reachable marking from m0.
Whereas with strong liveness, the
property must hold for all markings
reachable from m0, including
perhaps unfavorably chosen ones.
Therefore, this is definitely
a weaker property, which
therefore potentially more
Petri nets can satisfy.
What does the property say
in terms of the reachability graph?
It simply means that every transition t
must occur at all in the reachability graph.
So if a transition
t is drawn in the
Petri net, then it must
also occur in the reachability graph.
Because the reachability
graph covers all circuits
which are possible
from a reachable marking.
So the requirement "there must
be a marking reachable from
m0" is equivalent to "there must
be a node in the reachability
graph" from which one
can make a t-transition.
Then we
can look again:
Is this now the case
for our example Petri net?
You can see that
already in the Petri net:
Here we actually know, we
have already seen circuits where
t1 has been executed, as
well as t2 and t3.
If we fire t1, we can then
fire t2 and then also fire t3.
Then we have fired
all transitions at least once.
And that would be enough to
detect weak liveness of the Petri net.
Or we look at the
reachability graph and ask ourselves:
Does every transition t1, t2,
t3 occur here at least once?
Then we see: yes, t1
here, t2 here, t3 here.
That would
be enough.
Thus weak liveness would already
be present in the example.
In order to be able to check
this (this is also true for strong liveness),
the reachability graph
should be finite.
We know, in general,
reachability graphs can be infinite.
This check for strong or
weak liveness is possible if
the reachability
graph is finite.
Weak liveness can often be easily
decided even for infinite reachability graphs,
if already in a finite
part of them all transitions occur.
For this it is only
important that each transition occurs once.
So if you have a Petri
net and the reachability graph partially
already; if you just start to develop
the one you may not have finished developing
(because it may not be possible in finite
time, because it has infinitely many nodes); but
if after finite time you have already
seen every transition once, you can already say:
The underlying Petri net
was at least weakly alive.
To also prove strong liveness, one would
have to know the entire reachability graph.
And this is of course
difficult with infinite reachability graphs.
That would be
"strong and weak liveness."
What we have seen here is
that a Petri net can be weakly
lively even though it
contains a deadlock, a
marking from which no
further steps are possible.
That does not
argue against weak liveness.
It does, however,
speak against strong aliveness.
And this kind of deadlock, impasse,
of course it also has a definition.
Even if we have
already intuitively seen what
it means, and perhaps don't
need a formal definition at all.
Nevertheless, here
once written down:
So a Petri net is
said to have a deadlock (or
so far I had
sometimes said dead end)
exactly when there is a marking reachable
from m0 for which no transition is activated.
Of course, equivalently
for the reachability graph,
this means that there is a
node from which there is no transition.
So this corresponds exactly to
our informal question about dead ends.
It also means that this Petri
net contains at least one deadlock,
and we see that, for example, in
the reachability graph here, but also here.
To say "there is a deadlock" or
"the Petri net is not deadlock-free", it
is enough to
have detected a deadlock.
In fact, there is
also the term "deadlock-free".
This is said when a Petri
net does not contain any deadlock.
Which is important, which is often
done wrong in the exercise or exam:
This deadlock term says
exactly what it says.
So it doesn't
say, for example,
that somehow there is a place
from which there is no arrow.
This is often misinterpreted by
students, and then they argue
that the Petri net is deadlock-free or
not, and then they focus on whether
there are places in it (i.e.
circles) from which there are no arrows.
That is
not the criterion.
The criterion is what
is written here, or
that there are nodes in the reachability
graph from which there is no transition.
That is, nodes from
which there is no continuation.
That is the
criterion for deadlock.
Not somehow a reference to
places in the Petri net itself.
To be able to check that, again it
is important that the reachability graph is finite.
This check, in
this way, for that
the reachability graph
must be searched completely.
And that's only
possible if it's finite.
This also means that you can only answer
something like this, in the exam for example, for
finite reachability graphs or for
Petri nets with finite reachability graphs.
But of course the definition
is also generally applicable, it is
just not so
easy to check then.
This is our example from before,
we don't have to do anything else.
We don't need to look
at it again in more detail.
I had already referred
to the dead ends
when I discussed or rejected
the strong liveness for the example.
What else is
there to say?
So what does
it even mean, "strong"?
Why is the
"strong liveness" called strong?
Because it is stronger in
sum than the weak liveness.
So, in particular, it is
true that any strong liveness
Petri net is both
weakly liveness and deadlock-free.
And
vice versa:
A Petri net that is not
weakly lively cannot be strongly lively;
a Petri net that contains
an entanglement cannot be strongly lively.
This is true because we do
not have transition sets that are empty.
If we also allowed
empty transition sets in Petri
nets, then this statement would
hold here only with a precondition.
This would be a very
artificial case of having Petri
nets in which there
are places but no transitions.
Then, formally, the Petri
net is quite strongly alive,
and then this
statement would not hold.
Since it would then be
both strongly alive and deadlocked.
But we consider, we
have intentionally defined, Petri
nets only for
non-empty transition sets.
And then the statement holds as
it stands here, and there's this clear
connection of strong to
weak liveness and deadlock-freeness.
Okay, we've just discussed
this on the one example.
I'm going to discuss in a moment in
a separate video with examples in my whiteboard
app of different
combinations of the
different properties in terms
of aliveness and stuckness.
So looking at simple artificial
examples where certain combinations occur.
In particular, it will also be
a matter of clearing up the
misconception, which is also widespread and is often voiced
in exercises or the exam, namely that freedom from
inhibition, so to speak, is precisely
the difference between strong and weak liveliness.
It is true that from
strong aliveness follows weak aliveness
and freedom
from inhibition.
But it is not true that, so to
speak, exactly these two things must be present
for strong
aliveness to exist.
These are independent qualities
in a certain sense.
But we will be able to make this
clear to ourselves with the concrete small Petri nets.